Guide to the Ulysses S. Grant Family papers, 1860-1937 MS2157
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ulysses S. Grant Family papers
1860-1937
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885
Grant, U. S. (Ulysses S.)
MS2157
10 Linear Feet
Collection includes correspondence, diaries, clippings, scrapbooks, framed photographs, engravings, coins, busts, furniture and other papers and objects of Ulysses S. Grant and Ulysses S. Grant III. The material dates from 1860-1937
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The material was donated by Ulysses S. Grant III in 1950.
Historical or Biographical Note
Ulysses S. Grant (born Hiram Ulysses Grant) (1822-1885) was a U.S. general, commander of Union forces during the American Civil War (1864-1865), and the eighteenth President of the United States (1869-1877). Grant was born in Point Pleasant, Ohio in 1822.
Grant began his military career at West Point, and served in the army from the time of his graduation in 1843 until 1868. He served under Zachary Taylor during the Mexican War (1846-1848). Grant was promoted to the rank of Major General following his success at the battle of Vicksburg (1863). In March 1864, President Abraham Lincoln promoted him to the rank of Lieutenant General in command of all the armies of the United States. Grant received Robert E. Lee's surrender at Appomattox Court House on April 9, 1865.
In 1868 the Republican Party nominated Grant for President; he served two terms. He ran unsuccessfully for a third term in 1876 and again in 1880.
Grant married Julia Boggs Dent in 1848; they had four children.
Grant was a trustee of The George Washington University.
Grant died in July 1885 at his home in Mount McGregor, New York. He and his wife are buried in Grant's Tomb in New York City.
Grant's grandson, Ulysses S. Grant III (1881-1968), was a trustee of The George Washington University and served as its Vice President from 1946-1951.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence, diaries, clippings, scrapbooks, framed photographs, engravings, coins, busts, furniture and other papers and objects of Ulysses S. Grant and Ulysses S. Grant III. The material dates from 1860-1937. The collection consists primarily of material collected by the Grant family on the subject of Ulysses S. Grant.
Additional materials from this collection are held by the Luther W. Brady Art Gallery
Collection Organization
Organized into two series: Papers and Artifacts.
Diaries; Scrapbooks; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Photographs; Lincoln, Abraham; Grant, U. S. (Ulysses S.)
- Papers, 1860-1937; MS2157 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes correspondence, diaries, clippings, scrapbooks, other papers of Ulysses S. Grant and Ulysses S. Grant III. Of particular interest is a diary in three volumes kept by Ulysses S. Grant during a trip to Asia (including Aden, India, Burma, Singapore, Thailand, Vietnam, China, Hong Kong, and Japan) in 1879. Clippings deal with Grant, his Civil War service, his son Frederick Dent Grant, and the Grant monument in New York.
  - Address of Abraham Lincoln President of the United States and Reply of Ulysses S. Grant Commander in Chief of U.S. Army Upon Presentation to the latter of his Commission as Lieutenant-General, 03/08/1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    In the back of the bound item is a ribbon with an image of Grant and the words "Richmond Lieutenant U.S. Grant"
  - Clippings -- Important articles, some political attacks, for Ulysses to read ..., 1883 ca. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings -- Important old articles about General U.S. Grant for Ulysses from his mother, 1885 ca. --1915 ca. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings -- Grant in the War, 1860-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- U.S. Grant III and Francklyn Hogeboom, 01/20/1937-01/28/1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Diaries of Southeast Asia tour, 01/23/1879-07/26/1879 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harpers Weekly, 03/22/1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A memorandum made by General Grant, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Marcha Grant compuesta y dedicada al ylustre viajero C. Gral, Ulises S. Grant por Miguel Rios Toledano, 03/01/1880 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Well Come. para piano solo dedicada al Sr. General Ulises S. Grant por G. V. Jordan Niel., 1880 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1863-1885 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Images and Lee's General Order Number Nine reproduction, Circa 1865-1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Transfer from the GW Luther Brady Art Gallery, 2019 September 10 (Accession 2019.077)
    4 images of General Grant; image of Ordnance depot armies operating against Richmond; and Lee's general order number nine reproduced by Donnelley Deeptone Offset.
- Artifacts, undated; MS2157 Series 2; 9.75 Linear feet
  This series includes framed photographs, engravings, coins, busts, a board game, furniture and other objects. The objects were owned by Ulysses S. Grant, depict him and his family, and/or were created in commemoration of his achievements.
  - Busts of Ulysses S. Grant Please note: these items are not in a box, undated (Othertype BUSTS)
  - General Grant's Campaign Against Lee. Reproduced and Illustrated in the Parlor Game, entitled "Grant's Line.", 1868 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ulysses S. Grant, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    General note
    engraving labeled "Maj. Gen. Ulysses S. Grant" "Eng.d by J. C. Buttre."
  - Capt. U.S. Grant 1845, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    engraving labeled in ink "Capt. U.S. Grant 1845" engraved "copyright 1885 by Charles L. Webster & Co." "A H Ritchie N A Sculpt.d"
  - Julia Dent Grant [framed photograph], undated (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Grant Statue [framed photograph], undated (Box 4, Item 2)
  - Photograph of General U.S. Grant and his horse Cincinnati, undated (Box 4, Item 3)
  - Watercolor painting, undated (Box 4, Item 4)
  - Pouch with Ulysses Grant image (Box 4, Item 5)
  - Lt. Gen. U.S. Grant, 04/1866 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    F. Gutekunst, Photographer.
  - Commemorative of the services rendered the Republic by Ulysses S. Grant, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    "Commemorative of the services rendered the Republic by Ulysses S. Grant. Commissioned Brig. Gen. 1861, Maj. Gen. 1862, and March 2nd 1864 Lieutenant General and commander of the Armies of the United States of America. Commisnd General July 1866. Elected President 1868. Re-elected 1872."
  - Commemorative of Ulysses S. Grant, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Pressed copper (?) plates depicting various stages of Ulysses S. Grant's life, mounted on cloth-covered board.
  - Ulysses S. Grant medals, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Pipe, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    pipe in the shape of bust of Ulysses S. Grant
  - Cigarette and match case, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Pen, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Medal in wooden case, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Medal, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Medal, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Medal, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Medal, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Pins, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Case, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    case in shape of bust of Ulysses S. Grant
  - Figurine of U.S. Grant, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)